A Guide to the Alberta Arthurs papers FA1507
Rockefeller Archive Center
Alberta Arthurs papers
1980-2006
Rockefeller Archive Center
Arthurs, Alberta
Rockefeller Foundation
MEM Associates
Council on Foreign Relations
FA1507
4.46 Cubic Feet 10 LTR, 1 LGL, and 1 Half-LTR size Hollinger boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center by Alberta Arthurs in 2017.
Arrangement
The collection was divided into three series during processing in order to represent discerned systems of arrangement that the records' creator implemented. The first series contains a group of files that were arranged around a number of different subject headings. These headings appear to reference different projects and focus areas upon which Alberta Arthurs worked. The second series contains files that were grouped together under the heading "ABA Current and Personal" and the last series contains files that were grouped tougher under the heading "Miscellaneous". The miscellaneous heading on the third series and various filing notes discovered on materials throughout the collection indicate that these three systems of arrangement were not complete or intended to be fixed, but the decision was made during processing to incorporate those organizational schemes into the collection description in order to provide insight into the original order of the records.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Project files, 1980-2004
Series 2. Current and personal files, 1981-2003
Series 3. Other professional files, 1994-2006
Biographical / Historical
Alberta Bean Arthurs has provided leadership in the philanthropic, cultural, and higher education fields as a scholar, educator, consultant, and Rockefeller Foundation program officer. She served as Director of the Arts and Humanities Division at the Rockefeller Foundation from 1982-1996.
Arthurs was born in Framingham, Massachusetts in 1932 and married Edward Arthurs in 1960. Together, they have three children: Lee, Daniel, and Madeline. She earned her B.A. and M.A. at Wellesley College in 1954 and 1957 respectively and later received a Ph.D. in English at Bryn Mawr College in 1972.
In the two decades between 1957 and 1977, Arthurs held a number of teaching and administrative positions at Tuft University, Rutgers University, Radcliffe College, and Harvard University before becoming President of Chatham College. She would leave that position in 1982 in order to join the Rockefeller Foundation.
In her post-Rockefeller Foundation career, she has worked as a consultant for MEM Associates, directed the Project on Culture and Development at the Council on Foreign Relations, and served on numerous boards and committees for various cultural organizations.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the papers of Alberta Arthurs, a consultant in the cultural and philanthropy fields and a former Director of the Arts and Humanities Division at the Rockefeller Foundation. Most of the papers regard Arthurs' career in philanthropy from when she departed the Rockefeller Foundation in 1996 to about 2006. Papers, speeches, drafts, notes, proposals, research materials, correspondence, photographs, and conference materials provide evidence of the various projects Arthurs managed and supported during this time period. Some of the key focuses of these initiatives and studies include the relationship between nonprofit and for-profit organizations within the arts field, cultural policy, cultural diplomacy, the relationship between culture and development, the role of emerging technologies within the arts, communication and convening in the arts field, and convening for cultural policy.
Arthurs did much of her consulting through MEM Associates during the time that the collection materials document, and through her consulting assignments, board memberships, and other professional activities, she worked on projects with organizations like the Rockefeller Foundation, the Ford Foundation, the Center for Arts and Culture, the American Assembly, the Salzburg Seminar, UNESCO's International Fund for the Promotion of Culture (IFPC), Pew Charitable Trusts, the StreamingCulture program at the City University of New York (CUNY) Graduate Center, Grantmakers in the Arts (GIA), and the James Irvine Foundation among many others. The collection also contains records that Arthurs created through her position as Director of the Project on Culture and Development at the Council on Foreign Relations as well as records that show her participation at the White House Conference on Culture and Diplomacy in November 2000.
Some files within the collection do hold materials that originate from when Arthurs headed the Arts and Humanities Division at the Rockefeller Foundation. These records consist of a few speeches, papers, and grant project descriptions. Personal correspondence and photographs were also produced during Arthurs' tenure at the Foundation. Her and her husband Edward Arthurs' later work with the resident scholars and artists program at the Rockefeller Foundation Bellagio Study and Conference Center in the early 2000s is documented by notes, a report that they wrote about the program, and letters from different resident scholars and artists.
The processes that the records' creator employed for filing and using the collection files created three different groupings of material: 1) files organized around specific projects and subjects; 2) files marked current and personal; and 3) file marked miscellaneous. The distinctions in file organization between these sets of records are represented in the collection's three series.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Rockefeller Foundation; Humanities; Humanities--Research; Arts; Cultural policy; Ford Foundation
- Project files, 1980-2004; 1; 1.33 Cubic Feet About 3.5 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains a segment of files in the collection that were grouped together around different subject headings. The more structured and consistent system of arrangement for this series may suggest that it was the intended model of organization for the records in the other two series.
  Papers, drafts, notes, correspondence, project proposals, and research materials provide evidence of Alberta Arthurs' processes for working on the different projects associated with the subject headings on the files. Most of these projects were studies and initiatives she worked on as a consultant that focused on topics like cultural policy, cultural diplomacy, arts and technology, and the relationship between nonprofit and for-profit organizations in the arts field. Nevertheless, there are a few files under the humanities subject heading that contain documents created during Arthurs' time as Director of Arts and Humanities at the Rockefeller Foundation.
  - Humanities - Speech to Senate Subcommittee on Education, Arts, and Humanities, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Humanities - Reference material on the state of the Humanities, 1988-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Humanities - Article drafts, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Humanities - The Rockefeller Foundation Humanities Fellowships, 1999-2000, circa 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Humanities - Event invitations, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Humanities - Structural observations notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Humanities - Rockefeller Foundation Arts and Humanities Division publications, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Humanities - Rockefeller Foundation Arts and Humanities Core Strategies, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Humanities - Report of the Rockefeller Foundation Meeting on Humanities draft, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Humanities - Loose notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Humanities - Rockefeller Foundation Meeting on the Humanities/The Humanities in American Life, 1980-1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Humanities - The Journal of Arts Management, Law, and Society, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Arts and economics - Reference materials, 1981-2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Arts and economics - The Journal of Arts Management, Law and Society, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Arts and economics - Background to the general subject of culture and development notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Arts, technology, and intellectual property - National Dance Heritage Videotape Registry: A Report, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Arts, technology, and intellectual property - Brief Amicus Curiae for the Rockefeller Foundation in Support of Respondents, 1998 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Arts, technology, and intellectual property - Grantmakers in Arts (GIA) Conference, Cleveland, Ohio, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Arts, technology, and intellectual property - Report from the Fall 2003 Media Diversity Convening, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Arts, technology, and intellectual property - Background materials, 1996-2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Arts, technology, and intellectual property - The American Assembly, "Business Models and Technology", 2001 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Arts, technology, and intellectual property - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Arts, technology, and intellectual property - Reflections, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Cultural policy - A Pre-Feasibility Analysis Regarding the Establishment of a Citizen's Association for the Arts draft, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Cultural policy - Cultural Policy Briefing, Center for Arts and Culture/Grantmakers in the Arts (GIA), 1998 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Cultural policy - Background materials, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Cultural policy - Rockefeller Foundation in the Arts and Humanities, 1997-2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Documents regard cultural policy research.
  - Cultural policy - Workshop on Mediating the Experience of Art, Social Science Research Council (SSRC), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Cultural policy - The Arts and Humanities in Public Life conference mailing, circa 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Cultural policy - Fourth Annual Summer Cultural Policy Meeting - Change and Exchange: Cultural Policy and Transition briefing book, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Cultural policy - Building and Sustaining an Arts Policy Community conference, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Cultural policy - Cultural Policy Network Conference, Center for Arts and Culture, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Arts and business - Deals and Ideals, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Arts and business - Silicon Valley Community Ventures (SVCV), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Arts and business - Report given at a meeting of the Grantmakers in the Arts (GIA), Chicago, Illinois, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Arts and business - Memo to Joan Shikegawa at Rockefeller Foundation regarding Deals and Ideals study proposal, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Arts and business - Miscellaneous article drafts, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Arts and business - The Cultural Sector as an Emerging Investment Opportunity, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Arts and business - Nonprofit Capital: A Review of Problems and Strategies by William P. Ryan, 2000 October (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Arts and business - Attracting Private Capital to the Cultural Sector: Preliminary Summaries of Terms for a Proposed Fund, 1998-2001; File contains a still image. The image is a photograph dated November 1998. It depicts Alberta Arthurs standing in a group of people in front of a TV Guide Magazine poster display. (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - The 12th Man in Space Symposium: The Future of Humans in Space, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Proposals and consultancies, 2000-2003; File contains a floppy disk titled The Arts Chronicle. (Box 4, Folder 42-45)
  - The Arts Chronicle .csv text file, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Current and personal files, 1981-2003; 2; 1.23 Cubic Feet About 2 LTR and 1 LGLsize Hollinger boxes
  Series contains a group of files that were originally labeled with the heading "ABA Current and Personal". Due to the fact that there are more recently created documents in the other two series, the term current does not signify any real difference in date between the files in this series and the files in the rest of the collection. It merely reflects the records' creator's processes for filing and using the files. Some of the personal material in this series originates from Alberta Arthurs' time as Director of Arts and Humanities at the Rockefeller Foundation. These documents include photographs from different meetings and conferences Arthurs attended as well as correspondence she received about her departure from the Foundation. There are a few Official White House photographs amongst the personal photographs. They depict Arthurs with President Bill Clinton and First Lady Hillary Clinton at the dinner for the recipients of the Medal of Arts and Charles Frankel Prize and Arthurs with the First Lady at other meetings or events.
  Records in the professional files in the series provide more content and contextual information about some of the projects documented in the first series. These projects include the work Arthurs did on a study to assess the feasibility of a newspaper for the arts field as well as her work on a cultural policy convenings initiative. Papers, invitations, correspondence, and conference program materials also provide evidence of Arthurs' participation in the White House Conference on Culture and Diplomacy in November 2000.
  - Tokyo speech, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - The Humanities in the 1990s article, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - On Making Cultural Policy: Remarks to the first meeting of the Cultural Policy Network, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Report on the American Assembly Meeting of For-Profit/Not-For-Profit Arts Professionals, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - The Foundation of Knowledge: Reflections on Rockefeller Fellowships, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - The Arts and Humanities in Public Life conference mailing, circa 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - American Art, Vol. 10, No. 3 - National Museum of American Art, Smithsonian Institute, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Commentary: Taking Art Seriously, from American Art, Vol. 10, No. 3, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Grantmakers in the Arts (GIA) Newsletter, Vol. 7, No.2, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    General
    Includes Alberta Arthurs article "A Grantmaker's Goodbye," June 11, 1996.
  - Letter to the Presidential Search Committee for the University of Southern California, 1990 August 27 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - From the Geo-Political to the Geo-Cultural: The Role of Culture in Development, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Some Artistic Neighbors Try to Lower Their Fence - New York Times, 1997 May 31 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - The Humanities in American Life: Twenty Years Later, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - American Dance Festival (ADF) brochure, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - The Art and Impact of Documentary Film: A Program of Grantmakers in Film, Television and Video in association with National Video Resources and the Film Society of Lincoln Center, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Art and Money - New York Times editorial, undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Council on Foreign Relations service agreement for Culture and Development project, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - UNESCO's International Fund for the Promotion of Culture Council (IFPC), 1997 March 12 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Personal correspondence regarding Alberta Arthur's departure from the Rockefeller Foundation, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Personal correspondence, 1996-2002; File contains two still images. One photograph depicts Alberta Arthurs in a meeting, and the other photograph depicts Arthurs at the Salzburg Seminar.; File includes a floppy disk dated January 1999 and labeled "Chicago paper". (Box 5, Folder 65)
    File consists of letters, postcards, invitations, and a few photographs. Some of the items include computer photo prints of Alberta Arthurs at the 1999 Los Angeles Sacred Music Festival with the Dalai Lama, a letter from First Lady Hillary Clinton where Clinton thanks Arthurs for her support of the President's efforts on the arts, and correspondence regarding the Maine College of Arts' (MECA) symposium, ARTISTS NOW: Educating and Advancing Artists in a New World.
  - Chicago paper, 1999 January (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Salzburg Seminar - A Record of Session 354: The Contemporary Novel, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Salzburg Seminar - A Record of Session 371: Art, Religion, and the Shaping of Culture, 1992-1999 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Poems about Bellagio by Poets in Residence at the Villa Serbelloni, 2002 August (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Rockefeller Foundation memo regarding the Museum Program, 1995 May 30 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Speeches and papers, 1998-2001; File includes a floppy disk dated February 1999 and labeled "On Making Cultural Policy: to the Cultural Policy Network". (Box 5, Folder 70-71)
    File contains a copy of Alberta Arthurs' final remarks to the Rockefeller Foundation Board of Directors.
  - On Making Cultural Policy: to the Cultural Policy Network, 1999 February (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - A Sense of Urgency paper, undated (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Memo from Alberta and Edward Arthurs to Lincoln Chen regarding The Villa Serbelloni, circa 2001 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Social Imaginaries, 1998-2001 (Box 6, Folder 74-75)
    File contains a significant amount of documents regarding the November 2000 White House Conference on Culture and Diplomacy. Alberta Arthurs was a panelist for a workshop at the conference.
  - Rockefeller Foundation photograph file, 1987-1996; File includes numerous still images. Many are sets of photographs, and some are standalone photographs. There is one photograph negative. (Box 6, Folder 76-77)
    File is comprised of photographs and some other related documents. All of the photographs appear to have been taken during Alberta Arthurs' time at the Rockefeller Foundation. They all depict Arthurs with other individuals or by herself.
    Related documents and descriptions either attached or written on the back of the photographs can be used to learn the content and context of many of the pictures in the file. However, there are some photographs that have little or no associated description.
    Many of the photographs were taken at different meetings and conferences that Arthurs attended. There are also copies of official White House photographs that depict Arthurs with President Bill Clinton and First Lady Hillary Clinton between 1993 and 1995 and a set of pictures regarding the American Dance Festival's (ADF) dedication of its 1996 season to Arthurs.
  - Chronicle of the Arts Direct Mail Market Test, 2000-2003 (Box 6, Folder 78-79)
  - Correspondence and other miscellaneous materials, 1992-2002 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    File contains the confirmation of Alberta Arthurs' appointment as the Director of the Project on Culture and Development at the Council on Foreign Relations.
  - New Trends of Cultural Philanthropy - New Jersey State Council on the Arts Report to the Field, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Pew Trusts cultural policy convenings grant, 1999-2003; File includes a group of still images. (Box 7, Folder 82-84)
    The photographs contained within the file were enclosed in an envelope labeled Wildacres Switzerland Inn with a receipt printed in 2000. However, it seems that there might be two distinct sets of photographs within that group because the location appears different. The two sets of photographs may be from different cultural policy convening meetings.
  - Chronicle of the Arts, 2000-2003 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Indochina trip, 1981-1997 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Photography, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 87)
- Other professional files, 1994-2006; 3; 1.9 Cubic Feet About 4.5 LTR and 1 Half-LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Series contains a group of files that were originally labeled with the heading "Miscellaneous". The dates on the material show that they were the most recent documents added to the collection. This suggests that they may not have been properly incorporated into the filing systems used in the previous two series.
  A large number of files in the series regard the first National Performing Arts Convention (NPAC) in Pittsburgh in 2004. Alberta Arthurs headed the I-DOC Project which was established to document and study the conference, to track issues discussed during the conference and to provide feedback to participants in real time, and to deliver an assessment of the conference in a report. Materials in these files include responses to surveys the I-DOC team issued both before and after the conference, charts, and other materials used for assessment and analysis.
  The last few files in the series concern a part of the work that Arthurs did for the StreamingCulture program at the City University of New York (CUNY) Graduate Center. Arthurs' son Daniel headed this project which provided technical services and resources to cultural organizations seeking to upload audio and video content to their websites.
  - UNESCO's International Fund for the Promotion of Culture (IFPC), 2002-2004 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Cultural Diplomacy: Recommendations and Research - Center for Arts and Culture, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - MacArthur Fellows Program Roundtable on Creativity, Globalism, and Global Creativity Working Papers, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Cultural diplomacy, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Conference application, original, 2000 November (Box 12, Folder 132)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - confidential material.
  - Notepad, undated (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Center for Arts and Culture - International cultural policy meetings, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Talking Points - Globalization and Its Impact on Culture, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Conference on Strengthening International Educational and Cultural Exchanges - President's Committee on the Arts and the Humanities, 1999-2000 (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Michael Holquist talk - "The Role of Foundations in Foreign Language Study, 1920-?", 1999 (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Cultural policy - Working Dinner by The Secretary of State on Cultural Diplomacy, 2000 March (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - World Decade for Cultural Development, 1988-1997, UNESCO - Culture and Development: A Study, 1994 February (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Japan trip - Contacts/Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 8, Folder 99-100)
  - Individual artists' project (Holly Sidford - The Urban Institute), 2002-2005; File includes a set of still images. The photographs were taken at the 51st Venice Biennale in June 2005. There also a few photograph negatives of some of those pictures. (Box 8, Folder 101-104)
  - Pittsburgh Conference/I-DOC - Orchestra information, 1997-2005; File includes a still image. It is a photograph of Arthurs and a group of other individuals at the Salzburg Seminar. (Box 9, Folder 105-106)
  - Pittsburgh Conference/I-DOC - Shared arts network ideas, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Pittsburgh Conference/I-DOC - National Performing Arts Convention and affiliated conferences, 2003-2004 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Funding the arts, 1999-2003 (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - Pittsburgh Conference/I-DOC, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Pittsburgh Conference/I-DOC - Findings, codebook, schedules, etc., 2001-2004 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Pittsburgh Conference/I-DOC - Surveys and notes, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Pittsburgh Conference/I-DOC - Post-convention, circa 2004 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Pittsburgh Conference/I-DOC - Pre-convention, undated (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Pittsburgh Conference/I-DOC - Findings, circa 2004 (Box 10, Folder 115)